Guide to the Art Young Papers TAM.046
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Art Young Papers
1891-1955
1924-1944
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Young, Art, 1866-1943.
Frank, Adelaide Schulkind
Friedkin, Anna D.
TAM.046
14 Linear Feet in 9 manuscript boxes, 1 small flat box, and 5 oversize flat boxes
Art Young was a cartoonist and socialist. The papers include correspondence, original drawings, cartoons, clippings, postcards, original writings, printed material and catalogs of exhibits by artists working with political themes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Adelaide Schulkind Frank and Anna Friedkin in 1971. The accession number associated with this gift is 1971.004. Additional materials may have been donation by Albert Boni in 1972. In 2016 an accretion to the collection was purchased from Argosy Book Store, Inc. and transferred to offsite storage; in March 2023 this accretion was accessioned as 2023.017.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Biographical Note
Art Young (1866-1943) was a leading socialist cartoonist and humorist whose work appeared in The Masses(1910-1917) and elsewhere. He was born in Monroe, Wisconsin, studied at the Academy of Design in Chicago, where he first illustrated news stories and saw his cartoons published in various newspapers. In 1895 Young moved to New York where his work was published in Life and where he became a socialist and, in 1910, one of the founding members of the artists and writers cooperative that produced The Masses, a socialist monthly. Young's work was among that cited by the U.S. government as being in violation of the World War I-inspired Espionage Act. Young's work also appeared in The Liberator(1918-1924), which he helped establish, his own radical humor magazine, Good Morning(1919-1921), the New Leader, the New Masses, The Nation, and elsewhere.
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence (principally outgoing), clippings, pamphlets, sketches and cartoons by Young, printed material and catalogs of exhibits by artists working with political themes including Maurice Becker, Edmond McKenna, Archibald J. Motley, Jr. and Herman Rose some of these contain illustrations. The bulk of Young's letters are to Adelaide Schulkind, Meyer Friedkin and Arthur Spingarn. The collection also includes an unpublished manuscript in various stages. There is one letter each from William Gropper and Will Durant. The file on Young's death includes letters from John Haynes Holmes and Young's relatives. There are three original drawings, clippings from newspapers and periodicals, including the New Masses, containing cartoons by and articles about Young, a set of twelve postcards, How to Cure World-Unrest, New Year's cards (1936-39, 1941-44), an illustrated envelope (1943) designed to accompany an affixed poster-stamp by Gilbert Wilson, "Unity for Victory," on the theme of black-white unity, a typescript of Young's Thomas Rowlandson(1938), a biography of the 18th century cartoonist, publication correspondence for Young's autobiography, Art Young, His Life and Times(1939), including a letter from John Nicholas Beffel, and Young's last will and testament.
Arrangement
Folders for the original donation are arranged alphabetically. Materials in the 2023 have not been arranged by an archivist; original order is unknown.
Appraisal
Newspaper clippings from the 2023 accretion were appraised out of the collection.
Postcards.; Wills; Cartoonists.; Right and left (Political science).; Clippings (information artifacts); Art, American -- 20th century; Socialism -- United States.; Obituaries.; Manuscripts for publication.; Exhibition catalogs.; Caricatures and cartoons.; Drawings (visual works); Wilson, Gilbert.; Holmes, John Haynes, 1879-1964; Spingarn, Arthur B. (Arthur Barnett), 1878-1971.; McKenna, Edmond; Rose, Herman.; Motley, Archibald John, Jr., 1891-1981; Durant, Will, 1885-1981; Frank, Adelaide Schulkind; Friedkin, Meyer; Gropper, William, 1897-1977; Young, Art, 1866-1943.; Becker, Maurice, 1889-1975; Beffel, John Nicholas; Frank, Adelaide Schulkind; Friedkin, Anna D.
- Inventory
  - Art Young: His Life and Times (flyer and special issue of New Masses), 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Autobiography: Contract for, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Becker, Maurice: Exhibitions, Clippings, Drawings (includes watercolor sketches on postcards and 2 sketches of Eugene V. Debs), 1942-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Beffel, John Nicholas: Profiles of AY ( New Yorker) and AY sketch of Beffel, Mar 2, 1935, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Belsky, Ben: Letters to, 1933-1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings: About AY, New Masses, 1913-1925, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings: AY Drawings, 1918-1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings: AY Drawings (periodicals, proofs and copies), 1891-1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Death: Memorial Meeting, Estate, Correspondence, Obituaries, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Direction: Art Young Issue (Vol. 7, no. 2), Apr 1944-May 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Drawings, Original, b&w, ink [3]Contents: 1. Silhouette. [With inscription "To my friend John Nicholas Beffel from Seneca Ill. From his heighbor. Art Young of Monroe Wis. Bethel, July 21, 1935"], signed "Art Young" 2. "Collis P. Huntington on board the Teutonic," signed "AY" nd 3. "It Surprised Him [penciled caption]" signed "Art Young" 1930 [two bearded, hatted farmers in ragged dress in a field; with text below, as follows- John Presley: "I see by the Clarion that they're goin to bring the log of the Mayflower over here." Hiram Harrow: "Gosh! I didn't 'spose there was a splinter of the old boat left"], 1930, 1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Durant, Will: Letter to AY, Jan 5, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Exhibitions and Publications (AY, Others), 1934, 1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Friedkin, Meyer [Mike]: Letters to (some illustrated), 1928-1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Gropper, William: Letter to Ann and Meyer [Friedkin], Aug 5, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Horn of Plenty [cartoon], undated (Box 1, Folder 15A)
  - Jesus Christ ["Reward" Drawing with text], undated (Box 1, Folder 15B)
  - Last Will and Testament, Book Contract, 1935, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - McKenna, Edmond: Exhibition, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Motley, Archibald J. Jr.: Exhibition of Paintings (catalogue), 1928 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Postcards: How to Cure World-Unrest [set of 12], undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Postcards: New Years, 1936-1939, 1941-1944 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Rose, Herman: Exhibitions, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Schulkind, Adelaide: AY Letters to, 1936-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Spingarn, Arthur: AY Letters to, 1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Thomas Rowlandson [typescript] by AY, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Thomas Rowlandson: Exhibition Catalog with Drawings by AY, New Art Circle, New York/Munich, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Wilson, Gilbert Contains: postcard from AT; Contains: "Our Common Destiny," a printed envelope, illustrated by AY, with [and referring to] a postage stamp by GW, "Unity for Victory: Minorities are vital to victory -F.D. Roosevelt", 1943 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Photographs of AY, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Oversize Pages (mostly from The Masses), undated (Box Shared Tamiment XOS001, Folder 1, Box 1, Folder 28)
  - This Campaign in Cartoons, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 29-31)